Guide to the Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 8, Awards and Memorabilia, 1957-2010 TJU.2010.01.08
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 8. Awards and Memorabilia
1957-2010
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Specter, Arlen
TJU.2010.01.08
73 boxes 73 records center boxes, plus oversize material
The Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 8. Awards and Memorabilia contains awards, honors, achievements and gifts received during Senator's Specter's career. Specter served as U.S. Senator from 1981 to 2011, making him the longest-tenured Pennsylvanian senator. The group includes plaques, diplomas, certificates, and assorted memorabilia items.
Custodial History
Material was transferred to the care of Philadelphia University in 2010-2011 from the Federal Records Storage Facility in Suitland, Maryland, as well as the Senator's Washington, D.C. and Pennsylvania offices. The physical material was transferred to the University of Pittsburgh in 2014, with the exception of selected photographic and memorabilia items that remain at the Arlen Specter Center's Roxboro House for display. In 2016, Philadelphia University merged with Thomas Jefferson University, and is now known as Thomas Jefferson University- East Falls campus.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Arlen Specter to Philadelphia University in 2010. Philadelphia University and the University of Pittsburgh entered into a partnership to jointly manage the collection in 2013.
Biography
Born in Wichita, Kansas, on February 12, 1930, Arlen Specter came to Pennsylvania to attend the University of Pennsylvania. He married Joan Levy in 1953, and graduated from Yale Law School in 1956. He became assistant district attorney in Philadelphia in 1959. In 1962, Specter was recommended to serve on the Warren Commission, assembled to investigate the assassination of President John F. Kennedy. As part of the Commission, he was responsible for co-authoring the proposal of the "single bullet theory," determining that one bullet struck both President Kennedy and Texas Governor John Connally. Specter ran for Philadelphia district attorney in 1965, switching his Party membership to Republican in order to unseat the incumbent Democrat. He was successful, and served as district attorney from 1966 to 1974.
After an initial failed run for Senator and then for Governor of Pennsylvania, Specter was elected to the U.S. Senate in 1980. He would stay in this position from 1981 to 2011, making him the longest-tenured senator in Pennsylvania's history. During this time, he was a member of a number of Committees: Judiciary (1981-2011; Chair, 2007-2007), Appropriations (1981-2011), Veterans Affairs (1981-2011; Chair, 1997-2001 and 2003-2005), Select Intelligence (1985-1991; 1995-1997; Chair, 1995-1997), Special Aging (1991-1995; 2007-2011), Governmental Affairs (1997-2001; 2003-2005), and Environment and Public Works (2001-2003; 2009-2011).
Though elected as a Republican, Specter was a moderate on many issues, including healthcare reform, immigration, and abortion. He would often cross party lines, such as in voting against the confirmation of President Ronald Reagan's nominee Judge Robert Bork to the Supreme Court in 1987. Specter would again come into the spotlight during a Supreme Court nomination process in 1991, for his cross-examination of Professor Anita Hill regarding her allegations against nominee Clarence Thomas. In 1999, he would vote against the charges brought against President Bill Clinton, giving an answer of "not proven" to reflect his belief that Clinton had not received a fair trial.
As Senator, Specter championed a number of causes and influenced many legislative areas. He was frequently a member of Congressional Delegation trips, particularly to the Middle East, where he would speak out on the cause of freedom from religious persecution and the importance of strong diplomatic relations. He was also a proponent of funding for medical research, including the use of stem cells. He advocated for strict crime laws, particularly for career criminals. His focus on benefitting Pennsylvania could be seen through the pursuit of grant funding opportunities and his attempt to prevent the closure of the Philadelphia Naval Shipyard in the 1990s.
With the worsening of Congressional partisanship in the late 2000s, Specter found himself frequently voting with his Democratic peers. After being one of only three handful of Republicans to vote for the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act in 2009, Specter found himself increasingly marginalized within his party. In April 2009, he returned to the Democratic Party, helping to ensure the passage of the Affordable Care Act. Seeking re-election in 2010, he was defeated in the Democratic primary by Joe Sestak.
Specter's 30-year tenure in the Senate concluded in January 2011. After leaving the Senate, he partnered with Philadelphia University (now Jefferson-East Falls) to establish the Arlen Specter Center for Public Service. In the fall of 2012, Specter, who had previously beaten Hodgkin's lymphoma in 2005 while serving as Chair of the Judiciary Committee, was diagnosed with cancer. He died on October 14, 2012, aged 82.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
The Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 8. Awards and Memorabilia comprises 73 boxes of material, plus additional oversized items, which document awards, honors, achievements, and events during Senator's Specter's career. As this material has no distinct arrangement scheme, interested researchers should contact Archives & Special Collections for inventory lists of the contents of this group. The group includes plaques, diplomas, certificates, and assorted memorabilia items.
Arrangement
Group 8 has no defined arrangement scheme, as materials were grouped and stored as space allowed. Interested researchers should contact Archives & Special Collections for inventories of the content.
Related Material
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 1. Pre-Senatorial Career Files, 1953-1980, TJU.2010.01.01
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 2. Legislative Files, 1965-2011, TJU.2010.01.02
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 3. Personal, Political and Official Files, 1944-2010, TJU.2010.01.03
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 4. Office Administration Files, 1962-2010, TJU.2010.01.04
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 5. Constituent Services Files, 1976-2007, TJU.2010.01.05
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 6. Public Relations and Media Files, 1972-2010, TJU.2010.01.06
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 7. Campaign Files, 1976-2004, TJU.2010.01.07
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 9. Photographs, 1930-2010, TJU.2010.01.09
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 10. Electronic Records, 1980-2010, TJU.2010.01.10
Memorabilia; Politicians; Specter, Arlen; United States. Congress. Senate
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1263)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1264)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1265)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1266)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1267)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1268)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1269)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1270)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1271)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1272)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1273)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1274)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1275)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1276)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1277)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1278)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1279)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1280)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1281)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1282)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1283)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1284)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1285)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1286)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1287)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1288)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1289)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1290)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1291)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1292)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1293)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1294)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1295)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1296)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1297)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1298)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1299)
- Awards and memorabilia, 1957-2010 (Box 1300)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1301)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1302)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1303)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1304)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1305)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1306)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1307)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1308)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1309)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1310)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1311)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1312)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1313)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1314)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1315)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1316)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1317)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1318)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1319)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1320)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1321)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1322)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1323)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1324)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1325)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1326)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1327)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1328)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1329)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1330)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1331)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1332)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1333)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1334)
- Awards and memorabilia (Box 1335)